And I find the rule in trading is that
if it is difficult, it's the right
decision. Whereas if it's easy, it's the
wrong decision. So I'm writing that
down. Generally speaking, the harder it
is and more difficult it is to do is
because you're fighting the natural
human emotion or the natural human
choice. And you know, the natural human
choice is to hold a loser and hope that
it turns into a winner. And the natural
human choice for winners is to take the
money off the table as soon as it's
showing green. I think one thing that
stands out for me from when I started in
the beginning in the late '90s early
2000s, it was pretty easy to be
consistent and make a small amount of
money. But it was really hard to make
big money. Whereas I find now, it's much
harder to get consistent and to get that
baseline of performance. But once you're
there, it's a lot easier to make a lot
more money in these markets today than
it was when I first started. I really
think that surrounding yourself with
other successful, talented, hard-working
people rubs off on you. You rub off on
them. And that uh that continuing circle
leads to people having greater levels of
success than if you were trading by
yourself.
>> What would your trading look like if
capital wasn't the constraint? That's
the reality for most traders. It's not
skill holding them back, it's size.
Trade the pool changes that. Step into
the US equity markets with up to
$200,000
in buying power without committing your
own capital. Full access to stocks and
ETFs, long or short, executed with the
precision and freedom serious traders
expect. Your performance is measured by
one standard, disciplined risk
management and consistent execution.
Meet that standard and you operate at
scale. No subscriptions, no ongoing
obligations, just a clear path forward.
For those ready to trade beyond
limitations, this is the next level.
>> Markets, [music] speculation, and risk.
This is the Chat With Traders podcast.
>> [music]
>> Hi traders, welcome back to another
episode of Chat With Traders. Very
excited for this one as today's guest is
Jason Berry, a trader whose career spans
nearly three decades across some of the
most competitive future markets in the
world. So, Jason's first exposure to
trading came as a floor clerk on the
London International Financial Futures
and Options Exchange during the final
years of open outcry. From there, he
connected with traders who brought him
in to help launch a trading office in
Dublin, an opportunity that became the
start of a long and highly successful
career in the markets. His early trading
success quickly led to a second calling,
and that is developing traders. So, over
the last 27 years, Jason's trained well
over 200 traders with several going on
to exceptional success themselves. He
later co-founded Positive Equity that
began in Dublin, later expanded into
Croatia where Jason's now based. But
really what makes Jason's record
especially remarkable is the
consistency. In fact, he's known as Mr.
Consistency. We're going to dive into
that. Over the last 14 years, he's only
had five losing months. That's a level
of durability and risk control very
rarely seen in trading. Listeners may
also recognize several other Market
Wizards that have been on Chat With
Traders as now Jason Berry is going to
be in the next Market Wizards book, The
Next Generation. Other traders, Rick
Bensignor was on episode 293, The Art of
the Wait. Lucas Froelich, episode 259,
Tessa and Ian interviewed them. And then
Christian Koolamagi, episode 212. That
was with Aaron. Aaron also interviewed
Lance Brightstein who joined Aaron on
episodes 228, 229, and 236. So, now
Jason joins that select group of traders
featured in the upcoming Market Wizards,
The Next Generation. So, Jason,
congratulations and welcome to Chat With
Traders. How are you?
>> Yeah, all right. It's kind of weird to
hear all those accolades.
>> Yeah, I mean, incredible. I want to
rewind time a little bit and let's learn
about Jason from your youth. I mean,
what Where did you grow up, and what was
your introduction to trading?
>> I have a an exceptionally strange
upbringing. My parents were hippies, so
I grew up on the side of a mountain
until the age of about 5 or 6 in
northern California, maybe 20, 30, 40,
50 miles from a
commune in the middle of the US national
parks. There was a piece of land that
was carved out that my my dad sold to
other hippies, and there was a small
community that lived around this place
called the Forks of Salmon.
>> What was that [clears throat] experience
like for you?
>> Uh
What was that experience like? Um
skinny dipping, barefoot, horse
horseback riding, a type of farming,
living off the land, no running water,
hand-pumped, electricity uh
non-existent, kerosene lamps, like
Little House on the Prairie kind of
stuff, but in the middle of the forest.
And uh yeah, it was a I don't know, it's
kind kind of idyllic looking back. It
was the late '70s. God, it makes it
sound so long ago saying that. It was
late '70s, and there's uh just a big
part of the population or part of the
population that just was escaping modern
uh life, and my parents chose to live uh
yeah, in the middle of nowhere. And the
nearest gas station was 20 miles away,
and the nearest grocery store was was
50.
>> [laughter]
>> So, how did you go about from living on
the side of the mountain isolated to
finding
trading? I mean, what was your
introduction like?
>> Introduction was probably I graduated
from college and uh was looking at jobs
overseas. I studied in in France for a
year as a as a high school student, and
I kind of got the the bug or the desire
in life to live overseas. Um I lived
with a family, and for whatever reason
they just really appealed to me living
in uh living in Europe or living outside
of the US. So, when I graduated from uh
college, I got my MBA and was looking
for for different jobs. One of them was
working in
in Russia doing democracy building
stuff. The This is
98. So, the wall is is down and Yeltsin
is in power and there's a big open
society, I guess, growing in in Russia.
It ended up not going anywhere, but at
the time was Yeah, like a democracy
style building style job. Uh
the other one was with
What's it? JP Morgan or Morgan Stanley
in in Tokyo.
Uh sort of like a IT  finance
job. I can barely remember, so long ago
now. And the other was working with my
cousin who needed a clerk for
for his job on the I'm not going to say
the mouthful, but on we call it LIFFE.
You said it earlier.
And
I was like, "Yeah, sounds interesting."
Was in London. I could get a an
automatic visa for a year. There's an
agreement between the US and
Britain. And so, I just went over and
was his clerk for 4 9 months on the
floor 2 years before everything went
electronic. It was supposedly the most
advanced trading floor in the world and
that the trades were cleared
I don't know if they were cleared during
the day or within half an hour or an
hour of the end of the day. But, it was
all still very much paper to computer.
So, traders would trade on a piece of
paper or trade with each other, write
down their trades on a piece of paper,
hand it to the clerk, that was me, and
my job was to take it around to the
clerks
that were inputting the trading data
into computers. And a trader would do
the exact same thing on the other side
and their clerk would do the same thing.
>> Very interesting. So, what was that
experience like? And also, what what was
the criteria to be like a clerk back
then? What What kind of resume did you
have have have?
>> Uh for me it was just straight-up
nepotism.
Uh, he was my first cousin, one of two,
uh, one of three, pardon me, excuse me,
one of four. And, uh,
and he needed somebody in short notice,
and I was happily happily to fill in the
fill in the role. His clerk had just
become a a an actual trader on the
floor, and so he was uh shorthanded.
Most people who were clerk had
clerkships on the floor were from around
the city of London, the East End of
London. Uh, most [clears throat] would
graduate from high school, get their
They call them A levels, which is uh I
think it's a test uh like the SATs or
something. Um, but I think you could
finish high school at that time at 16.
So, there are a lot of 16, 17,
18-year-olds that were coming down to
the floor
um looking to become traders or be a
part of that environment. Um, become
traders or brokers.
Uh, my cousin was a was a prop trader,
was backing himself.
And there were people that just wanted
to come down and uh do one of those
jobs, and the clerk role was the first
role in the door to be able to to have
that opportunity to either meet somebody
or to learn learn the ropes.
>> Yeah. What What was the experience like
for you? I mean comparing today to then,
I mean the electronic trading versus
then, I mean what What's the compa-
>> The comparison uh total different set of
skills. The your ability to make money
was both a combination of being able to
read the market, well, that was probably
secondary was your ability to get good
fills from brokers that were friendly
with you. Um I think uh most traders
would take the brokers out on a regular
basis for drinks or or dinners or what
whatnot.
>> Wait, so you're saying you would get
better fills if you're more friendly?
>> Yeah, cuz the the it's it was all
it's all open outcry, so people are
looking at you. You're filled, you get
five, you get 10, you get a 100.
Um
and
your ability to be friendly with the
broker was an advantage to people who
weren't friendly with the broker cuz you
could get one price better
um when uh when stuff was traded. And
that just that was your piece of that
that could be your piece of edge to to
stay in the trade or even just make a
tick just to flip the tick.
>> That sounds like definitely it's good
edge.
>> That's very
Yeah, significant edge. And then that
was it.
That was it.
>> Uh So, what other
>> As well I mean
>> Wow. What are some other edges that
you've seen ex- I guess ex-
exploited?
>> I mean they're called they're called
elbow trades and you're standing next to
the broker who's handing out tons of
uh size or buying up stuff and
uh you get that half tick better than
where the market's trading and you know,
the market can trade two or three prices
uh at the same instant. There are people
that were watching the the pits. Um
I think they were blue coats or uh
I can't remember, but they're market uh
surveillance and they would make sure
that there was uh
if people are following the rules, but
there was definitely a lot of wiggle
room for
for for the way trades were handed out
or traded with on the on the floor.
>> Man.
>> But again, I was only there for 9
months, so I'm sure there's
>> There's other corruptions maybe perhaps.
>> know, I was watching one of the
corruptions but in let's say
inefficiencies inefficiencies.
>> Okay, so here's another inefficiency. I
was watching one of your other podcasts
and I and I heard you talk about how a
floor trader from maybe London was
calling in maybe to a floor trader in
Chicago and you could hear right the
orders going through and maybe there was
the time discrepancy, right? Where maybe
you could get in before this whale got
in and that kind of a thing. Is that an
edge? Perhaps that was even
>> Well, that's being I I yeah, I I know
that I know the I know the instance
you're talking about or the example. So,
back in the old days when you had to
wear a suit to come on to the floor, uh
it was super formal. Um you weren't
allowed to have mobile phones. You
weren't allowed to have computers or
tablets, um even though they did exist
in the late '90s. And the exchange was
very anti-technology.
And little by little it started to uh to
change. Um but one of the one of the
traders I saw didn't have his mobile
phone, but had a an earbud or a headset
or whatever the smallest form of headset
was back then. And it was connected to
some sort of transponder to somebody
else's phone
uh somewhere else in the building. And
so he would listen to I think it was in
the Gil pit. He would listen to the US
10-year and how the US 10-year was
trading in Chicago and have that uh
immediate edge of what the 10-year was
doing. And the 10-year, like today,
would drive, you know, most of the bond
markets depending on what uh what was
happening. So, if say on
you know, non-farm payroll, all of a
sudden, you know, 10-year's up 10 ticks,
that's going to be a big move for the
Gilts. And uh
that trader would have that advantage.
I'm not sure if it was allowed or if
people noticed or people cared, but it
was a definitely a very visible uh a
visible form of edge that that trader uh
that trader came up with.
>> Wow. I mean, do you see anything today
that stands out as an edge
like those from back then? I mean,
>> No, I mean, all the easy stuff is
gobbled up. It's all in computers now,
you know.
>> Right. Yeah. And I want to get into that
as well, but um I want to ask you about
becoming a a market wizard. Now,
congratulations on that. Uh what what
was that
>> It only took 25 years.
>> 25
>> [laughter]
>> Mr. Consistency for 25 years. I mean,
what how did you find out about it? How
did that come about?
>> Uh
how did it come about? Um
a
a person over here organized a
conference and invited Jack Schwager to
come to Zagreb. And I
was I heard about the the guy who was
organizing it and uh
and I said, "Yeah, definitely want to go
to that conference, be involved." Um so
we sponsored part of the conference and
uh ended up meeting Jack at uh
drinks or lunch and I talked with him
over the weekend and said, "Hey, if you
ever uh
if you ever uh
are look If you ever do another book, um
give me a shout. I might have a number
of people to
uh send your way."
And uh lo and behold, a couple years
later he calls
and uh
I sent him uh I solicited names from uh
people that I know.
Most people didn't uh didn't want to to
be involved cuz they're traders and have
a private life.
And uh there's no
appeal to be in the public uh in the
public eye at all.
And uh one guy went through with the
interview
um and in the end didn't want to do uh
to do it either. And uh I Jack asked me
if I had anybody else. Again, same same
process. Found another guy but didn't
want to be involved. Found one guy and
he didn't uh didn't qualify.
And then Jack uh or George, can't
remember who, said, "What about you? Um
you've been doing this a long time." And
I said, "I'm a I'm a journeyman uh
trader in in my mind. Um I'll send you
the stats and you guys can
can decide on your own." And uh I was
kind of to be honest a bit sheepish
about it because uh
I don't necessarily see myself as a uh
as a market wizard. Um There are there
days when I'm the best trader and
those are not that often anymore cuz
there's a lot of smart talented guys
around me.
Um
And there years when I've been the best
trader but again that has been a few
years now.
Uh
but I sent him the the the stats and uh
it took a long time. So, I I don't know
if you've seen any of the
any of the criticisms from the inter
interweb about uh how people are
qualified for this uh
for uh for being in the book, but uh
George and Jack uh went through 15 years
of
of uh
clearing statements and just poured over
them to figure out whether I should be
in the book or not. Um
>> Yeah, I was going to ask what are they
What are they What is George What What
is Jack What's for? I mean, and if we're
in traders, but hey I mean, you're
spelling it out there. It really dives
into the track record.
>> Oh, no. They They They won't won't even
consider talking to you unless you have
his official statements from the clears.
So, my back office sent over all the
statements, had to dig back through.
I don't think I don't think any of them
are physical. I think they're all still
electronic, but still 15 years of
electronic statements. You know, I trade
uh
hundreds to thousands of lots a day.
Uh that's a lot of data for them to to
be going through. Anyway, so I got them
all the data. They came back and they
said, "Dude, you are the second most
consistent uh
uh trader we've ever looked at. Your
stats don't make any sense to us.
They're so consistent.
Uh we'd love to have you in the book."
>> Wow. So, [clears throat] consistency.
And nearly three decades of it. Trading
since what? 1999? No losing years, just
a few losing months. I mean, how do you
define risk in your own framework? I'm
uh curious like what what your risk
reward really looks like. What What does
that What does that number look like?
>> Risk reward? Um it's tricky cuz uh as a
as a prop trader you're trading a book.
You're trading on behalf of the firm.
You know, I have a certain amount of
money that's that's down as risk
capital, but it's largely down to the
relationship with the clearer and and
their perception of your risk and
profile and because we're a a
collaboration of traders, our risk
profile is lessened to an individual
basis because we all trade in different
directions and can have one trade on in
this way and other trade that way and
they all kind of overlap in many ways
and our outright exposure ends up being
a lot less. Like an insurance pool if
you will. Like you know, if you're an
individual, your your rate is X a month,
but if you're in a in if you're part of
a group, your your rate is less. So So
looking risk reward on individual
trades, it's hard for me to hard for me
to say. I can tell you [clears throat]
my, you know,
best months versus worst months, best
days versus worst days are multiples of
5 to to 20.
>> Yeah. I mean, if you don't put up with
losses, it doesn't sound like it. It
almost sounds like a ride or ride out
approach. When you get into the trade,
it's going to work or it doesn't. Is
that fair?
>> Well, I I think probably the biggest
the biggest fallacy out there that is
that every trade has has I mean, all
trades have risk, but there are certain
trades that you can put on that just you
know are unless there's some news that
comes out while you got the trade on,
they're just going to be winners. And I
have a core set of trades that I know
that if they trade, it's going to be a
winner. And so it's it's not necessarily
that my risk management abilities are,
you know, awesome or that I'm super
risk-averse, it's that my edge is really
compelling. I am risk-averse, but at the
same time, you know, I'm probably in the
middle of of the traders I see on a
daily basis. I'm probably in the middle
of the sort of risk adversity
personality of many people in the firm
that are a lot more risk-averse than I
am. And then there are plenty that are
more risk that take on more risk than
than I am
>> [snorts]
>> than I have.
>> Uh give us an example of one of those
trades for you that you have just a high
level of confidence and and do you size
that disproportionately to maybe, let's
say, you know, one of your other
>> Yeah, of course you try and get as much
as you can.
The The limit The limit really there
isn't how much I can
manage. It's how much the market is
going to give out. You know, when you
know when it's a when it's a all but
guaranteed winner, the market isn't
giving you thousands and thousands of
lots. It's uh smaller smaller lot sizes
and
more limited opportunities. Nobody likes
giving away money. So, you know, I have
half a dozen of these type trades that
maybe come off once a week or twice a
week, or maybe once a day, twice a day,
but in smaller numbers. Um but overall,
I have one that's, you know, I have them
that they're coming in on a regular
basis
as opposed to higher risk trades that
you can put on at any time with any
size, but the edge is a lot less and
your
your risk reward is isn't as good.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> The more competitive a market, the more
difficult it is to find an edge, the
less competitive.
But again, it's it's Again, it comes
really down to the the research and you
I can research certain trades and figure
out that they'll be that there's a high
degree of winners before I even look at
what the market is how it how the
market's actually trading in the order
book.
>> Mhm.
You know, do you
attribute that to experience? Um
I ask that because, you know, we're
we're entering a landscape now that's
very
systematically driven. But with your
level of experience and consistency,
like one would think like you
Mr. Consistency over here. I mean,
that's really attributed to experience,
right? Can you really even
put that experience into a system? Where
do you see that world going?
>> Do you mean putting putting the
experience putting putting my ability to
observe trades into a an automated
system?
>> Yeah, can you make a Mr. Consistency I
guess model AI program that can do these
trade Well, just size into these systems
like have the gut The guts this combined
experience over time, right? That tells
Jason like this is where you size in and
this is where you size out. Now, I've
watched some of your other interviews,
too, where you discuss Look, like part
of your process is anticipating events.
Like you don't necessarily wait for the
wars to happen. Like you have You
already have your plan in place in case,
you know, in case whatever war is going
to happen breaks out or if this ends.
So, you've predefined all this already.
Can you put that into a system?
>> Um yeah, for sure you can. Uh but uh my
my my abilities and my skills aren't in
programming black box
uh or making an algo. My My skill and my
abilities are just executing the trade
and identifying the trade as a as a
human being. That means that certain
trades are off limits to me. Um a lot
of, you know, a lot of the algo or
high-frequency type trades. I mean, I do
have some automated trades
um that uh that I do execute. But uh by
and large, it is uh
it's more of a point-and-click. Yeah,
it's a different set of skills to
program and to build automated trading
systems. Yeah. And one One as as as as
one of the guys in the uh on the floor
here said to me, "Hey Jason, guess which
one of the uh traders is the oldest of
the traders in that uh new Market
Wizards book?"
And uh you know, rhetorical question.
So, I'm on the I'm on the other end of
the the sort of programming and the algo
uh
set of skills. My My skills were were uh
you know, late '90s, early mid '80s
video game type skills in identifying,
you know,
using those skills in the markets as
opposed to being able to program or uh
work with programmers to to automate the
trading systems.
>> Heard heard you discuss the the video
games, too, where you've had some of
your trainees actually play games, maybe
for you to identify, you know, certain
uh
uh I don't know, certain traits they may
possess. Um
can you elaborate on that?
>> Sure. Uh we used to do it on a regular
basis. I think we stopped doing it
because I had kids and a wife and I
couldn't stay late after work. Um but
yeah, we used to play uh those
large-scale uh
shooting games um within the office on
the LAN.
Uh it's very similar
um
uh
It's a very similar experience
emotional- ly speaking. Um and that you
are in a game versus other people. Yeah,
they win or you win. You lose or they
lose. Uh
you know, like uh let's say in a in a
sniping game or in a game where you can
be a sniper, uh you can snipe people
three or four times from the same spot,
but eventually uh people are going to
realize that you're in that spot and
they don't get like getting shot, so
they they figure out a way to get around
that and to to get to you. Same thing in
the market. Nobody likes losing money
and if a a trade you've done
whatever amount of times keeps working,
at some point it's going to disappear
because nobody Again, nobody likes
nobody likes to lose money in the
markets.
Um the emotional roller coaster that you
go through from losing in a video game
versus losing in the market, very
similar. Um obviously the costs are
different. Um you know, it only costs
you time and emotion in a video game,
whereas uh in in the markets, it's you
know, money's on the line. But I think
the emotions are very much and the way
people deal with losses uh in video
games versus the markets are are very
similar. But losses and successes
successes.
>> Because losses are inevitable, right? I
mean whether in the game
>> Yeah, absolutely. It's just it's just
part of the game. It's part of the game.
>> So did you realize that
In
>> 1999 till now like clearly you just have
something that other traders don't have
because you've you've held the title Mr.
Consistency all these years. I mean what
do you possess and what do you see in
others because you've trained so many
individuals like what what is that that
you possess and maybe others have as
well where
is it just where there's no ego involved
with the trades where it's if it doesn't
work if it's invalidated you can take it
off or you let your winners run or you
size into your winners like what what do
you think it is about
that you've had such high levels of
consistency and I guess to follow that
up what do you see perhaps in some of
your trainees where you you say okay
they they got this trait that really can
you know progress them further in this
where you can can see a trajectory
there?
>> There's a huge advantage to trading with
other people around you. There's a huge
advantage to being surrounded by smart
intelligent
successful traders that if you are
trading on your own is denied to you.
It's a huge advantage of joining a team
that already has
10 20 30 40
>> So you've always traded with
groups of people?
>> Yep.
>> You've always well.
>> I think it's one of the it's one of the
things we have on our on our walls is
innovate together.
Um
it's such an advantage you know and I
don't I don't work with everybody in the
firm but I have the guys around me that
that that sit around me and we work
together on
on figuring out the markets and we are
individually responsible for the trades
that we make and for our performance but
we work together on figuring out edge
and exploiting edge and
trading strategies together.
Um but that that that's I would say
that's the largest the largest
advantage.
Um in that
when you are surrounded by other
talented, intelligent, hard working,
successful people, that all rubs off on
you
and you rub off on them.
Uh it's a it's a
the opposite of a vicious circle.
The a successful circle
um that uh feeds on itself
um that encourages it to continue. And I
think it's one of the biggest advantages
that uh people trading firms have over
people who are trading as individuals.
>> Yeah, that's incredible. I mean, it
makes sense. You know, trading in
isolation
can breed bad habits. I can very much
see that where that that makes And you
would know best out of anybody. Again,
you've you've trained so many
trained you say it's not
>> bad habits, but
you can take your foot off the pedal.
You can get distracted by life around
you. Um
cuz we have we wrestle with the same
thing with cuz now that uh trading is
electronic, we do have a number of
traders that are trading uh from home
offices.
Um some that do both. I do both. Uh
during the day I'm in the office and in
the evenings I'm at home.
Um
but there's a I I find there's a real
risk to trading by yourself
>> [snorts]
>> that
doesn't exist if you're in the office.
Um
there's a greater chance of oblivion um
trading outside the office outside the
office than there is for people who
maintain and stay in the office and
trade in the office and work with the
guys around work with the people around
them.
>> Do you think it's sufficient enough to
find chat rooms out there to be
associated with? Because you know what
the the lure for a lot of traders is,
you know, that they can
they can be to themselves. They can kind
of escape the world. They can have this
freedom to not be involved go to an
office. So, what what do you say to
those traders?
>> There are people [clears throat] who
uh and we have you know, we have a
number of of people in our firm that
trade uniquely from home but they are in
the minority and there's still a greater
chance
of oblivion trading [clears throat] at
home than people trading in the office.
It's you know that there's a bunch of
myths around trading you know
one trading is liberating and lets you
be your own boss
trading you can trade from home and
enjoy the pleasures of home office
it's get rich fast
you know all those sort of all those
myths they're out there that really
aren't true and are I don't know maybe
been created by by TV or by movies
the one you know be be your own boss and
and work at your own leisure man people
who do that
aren't really very successful for very
long or never even attain success
you know I take up a lot of time in the
summers but man it destroys my ability
to trade by the time September comes
around and I have a huge ramp up time
where I have to trade small and you know
get back into the the rhythm of trading
so
pretending that you have to work less
hard at this career as opposed to
another career like that's just a myth
>> So why do you think that is for the
summer do you think it's like you you
get you get rusty or do you think it's
just the market changes and you have to
kind of adapt to that okay
>> absolutely both
>> [snorts]
>> absolutely both you get rusty and the
market changes
you're you're not tuned into what
the
what the news cycle is
you're not tuned into the full risk on
or risk off
environment
you're not tuned into what's actually
moving the markets
the markets have changed the fills are
coming through differently the trades
are coming through differently.
Whereas when you're
when you are seeing the market every
day, you're witnessing the small changes
to the market. Um whereas if you're away
for a week, you've missed those 5 days.
If you're away for you're away for 2
weeks, you've missed those 10 days. And
those little changes over time add up to
big changes that are hard to adapt to.
>> All right, Jason. I'm going to try to
get you to divulge your secrets here
again from the 1999 on.
>> Well, because
all of my all of my traders enjoy your
podcast and will murder me if any pieces
of edge come out.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay.
Uh
let's try to get Okay, let's maybe
discuss then a prior like you you've
alluded to that maybe the edge has
changed over time. So,
can you discuss maybe edges you've
traded in the past with that can add
value to the traders listening that may
they can apply to their you know, their
own future. Yeah, some of some past
edges.
>> Uh
let's see.
Um
Well, I'll tell you one edge that's not
allowed anymore. Uh in the past
uh
the And I think maybe this is why
Bitcoin was so big for a lot of trading
groups over the last few years
um is that in the early in the late
2000s, there were no uh market market
manipulation rules. There were no market
uh MAR, what's it called? I should know
that off the top of my head. Uh
and so a lot I know I know a lot of
traders that uh
push size around in order books um to
get trades off that they wouldn't
otherwise be able to get off through
manipulation of the order books.
Um I know one guy in in Chicago who did
it until the rules were put in and then
he just retired a millionaire. He just
stopped trading. Didn't even try to
trade uh
uh beyond that.
Um but in terms of edge that used to
work, well, I news used to be edge. Um,
you know, you would you would hear the
news through the TV. Um, I remember
watching uh September 11th.
Um,
and or not watching it. And that traders
that were downstairs had a TV and uh
those of us who were upstairs, we didn't
have a TV. And those traders that had
the TV watched uh the they saw the
they didn't see the first plane and so
there was just market chaos, but they
saw the second plane and all the traders
just unloaded everything once they saw
the the images of the second plane
before it even hit the building.
Um, so information edge used to be
massive massive edge. And you could like
on the TV, never mind some, you know,
special news service or Bloomberg or
Reuters.
Uh, and now the news that kind of news
release
is
not really an edge anymore because it's
gobbled up by the high frequency algos
that are programmed to absorb that uh
absorb that edge. I think in one of the
previous Market Wizards uh books,
uh one of the one of the guys described
that uh that edge.
Um,
but stuff that won't get me in trouble
with the traders and and the and uh and
You're the stupidest in the markets?
>> Yeah.
>> Um, I'd say, you know,
biggest thing is just to get out there
and innovate and to spend time and spend
time in the markets and to look at to
watch markets.
Um,
and the better you know them, the the
better
uh you're are able to to trade them.
>> Yeah, I believe that, you know, the
first example you gave
got cracked [clears throat] down on. I
think it was 2010, like spoofing orders
became illegal, but like you said, there
was an
an edge there where traders capitalized
on and then maybe became too competitive
like the example you're giving where
it's like, "Okay, I'm done with this,
you know, after
being able to
>> If you're not even competitive, you go
to jail.
Or you get fined.
>> Right. Right. Right. Yeah. But post
2010, right? But prior to that
>> Um I can't remember when the rules uh
finally came in. Uh I I know that some
traders used to trade they knew there
was a spoofer who was active um and they
would trade against him um as best they
could uh knowing that he was spoofing
the market since so they they weren't
spoofing the markets themselves, but
they would see the spoofing going on and
they would trade against that trade or
with the trader they but they would they
would be active when that guy was active
in the markets.
>> Right. Yeah. Uh you know, you've
mentioned that innovate word a few
times. How important is it over your
career think to just constantly be
innovating because there's this I think
there's this uh
a traders think you know, I'm speaking
for myself, you know, first starting
where you think there's this finish line
maybe you know, you where you just make
it and you no longer have to
innovate any any longer. So how how
important do you think it is to
continuously
innovate and work on yourself?
>> The one thing I say to all my uh all my
guys is that uh treat yourself as a
trainee whether you're 1 year in whether
you're 10 years in
do all the things that got you
successful in the first place, you know,
everybody's got that initial uh for us
it's you know, 2 3 years before people
are are getting to a
a base level of success and those 2 or 3
years are them killing themselves to
figure out the edge. You know, the first
year is just learning curve of you know,
all the basics, but eventually you get
to the point where you're you know, a
full-fledged trader and you're starting
to make money, but to get to that point,
you know, you are
you're killing yourself look you know,
watching markets spending time in front
of screens
um you know, watching the tape as the
old uh I think that's reminiscent of a
stock operator quote.
Watching the tape is
is is
is so basic but
so much part of
the best trading advice you can get.
It is
and and the cost of that is time and I
think that's the
the
the problem for most people in that they
don't have enough time
>> [snorts]
>> to get to a point where
they've actually watched the tape for
long enough that they can actually start
seeing things.
I believe as with most things to become
a professional and to become a high
performing professional in in trading,
there's that 10,000 hours equation that
I can't remember which book it was.
Bounce I think it was Bounce.
Bounce I might have been another book
but there's a there's a concept. You got
to get 10,000 hours before you become a
real professional at something and once
you've had 10,000 hours of being in
front of the screens
and observing the markets, you get to a
certain level of comprehension where you
know which trades are good, which trades
are bad, which trades are dangerous,
where to size up, where to size down
and you see repeating repeating patterns
and repeating events repeating scenarios
that you know how to react to. And if
you do the math on 10,000 hours
of you know, working 8 hours a day or 10
hours a day or
killing yourself and working 18 or 20
hours a day
it's still a lot of years to get to that
point.
That's not saying that you know, once
you're 3 4 years in that you're not
going to be start getting to a certain
level of success. It's just saying that
once you get to you know, the 10,000
hours there's a much higher degree of
success, a much higher level of success
but most people never get to that
because they just don't have the time to
spend
7 8 years working on something that
isn't paying off
enough for them to put in that time.
>> Yeah. Jason, what trait do you see maybe
personality traits among your trainees
when they get signed up with you? What
can you see early on where you say,
"Hey, this is they they have it. They
have something here that can really take
them to that next level."?
>> That is a hard question.
Um
I think for
for every firm that's out there, there's
a different set of criteria
that they look for, that we look for.
And nobody knows for sure what the magic
[clears throat] set of traits is.
Um you know, we kind of do our best in
what we think,
but we regularly get guys that don't
match our [clears throat]
set of criteria
um that become successful.
Uh but in general, we look for high
performers in everything that they've
done from
high school and college to to
competitive sports.
Um historically, we've looked at poker
and uh
and competitive games, including video
games.
Um but anything where people have had to
have a disciplined
life
and
lifestyle choices
um that force them to
be disciplined with their approach to
their studying, their job, their
their sport, their competitive activity.
Um
and illustrate a
high level of
um performance in whatever it is
whatever the activity is that they that
they did. Um I like seeing
uh
activities where people have to beat
other people, either out-think them or
out-play them, not just out-strength
them or out-endurance them. Like
somebody that runs, uh does
ultra-marathons,
like fair play for you beat other
people, but it's less down to you
out-thinking that person and more down
to
you know, your practice and your life
discipline before you get to that point.
You know what I mean?
But
>> Right. I'm here on innovation. Thinking
of innovative ways, you know, to beat
them. Yeah.
>> Just clever ways to out- think your
opponent.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh
you know, you go one way, they go the
other way.
It's But in games and activities where
you have to out-think your opponent as
opposed to
out-endure them or out-discipline them.
>> Are there behavioral tells for you where
you think, okay, they their reaction to
a loss perhaps, you know, is your or
maybe they're not very curious.
>> Those are the easiest. Those are the
best. Those are the best.
>> Okay. [laughter]
>> Those are the best. That's the best tell
ever. And it it's only come every once
or comes every once in a while, but
those are the easiest. We once I was
once trained a guy
and he could not cut his losers. And I
went through with him for about a month
and a half and
normally people where I work with for,
you know, somewhere between a year and
two years before they either make it or
they don't make it. And this guy after a
month and a half, I was like, dude,
you just don't have it, man. You just
can't cut your losers and I got to let
you go.
And this was before
before simulation. So he was actually
losing money in the markets.
So he left, went to another firm and
I heard like a week or two weeks later
that he had a like a thousand euro day.
I was like,
did I make some mistake? Did I not see
something in this guy? Maybe, you know,
he was
>> Hm.
>> I made a mistake and he he clearly could
trade. And then, you know, the next
couple days heard he had a couple of two
and three grand days and then four and
five grand days and then 10 15 grand
days. And I was like, "Oh my god, what
have I done here? I've totally blown it.
Let this guy go and, you know, I let a
whale go." And then, uh about two, maybe
three weeks after he left,
then it came.
He
was down 100 and
80 190 grand
and uh had been spoofing in the S&P and
the Nasdaq.
The new firm that took him on
didn't have his limits in correctly and
he had unlimited orders
to play with in the markets.
And uh yeah, he did so.
He didn't make it. But, uh
those are the easiest to find. Uh
Less less less easy, um
I had a class of uh three guys. One of
the guys would always cut the uh loser
too soon, had amazing discipline and was
super tight. The other guy was uh
looser, but still knew when to to cut.
Um
and
the third guy was always cutting 10 or
20 or 30 or some amount of time
uh later than the other two guys and he
ultimately didn't make it. And it was It
was seconds difference between the three
cuts. Let's say the first guy would cut
it at 10 seconds, second guy would cut
it at 20 and the last guy would cut it
30. And that guy just never made it. He
uh he couldn't he couldn't cut it for
whatever reason at [clears throat] the
right time early enough before it did
too much damage.
Um but those are the easy That's an easy
one to to find. Once you find one of
those, you're like thankful,
"Thank you. That's an easy uh an easy
decision." The the The most difficult is
somebody who works hard, is disciplined,
and like does everything you that you
ask, is super coachable, takes on all
feedback. Um those are the most
difficult because at the end of the day
you got to perform and those guys that
don't perform, you give them most amount
of time. When somebody does everything
right and and listens to you in every
every way possible and works as hard as
hard as they can,
those are the most difficult because
they're doing everything right, but
they're just not figuring it out.
Um, [snorts]
one of the easiest uh to you know, one
of the easiest traits to see is just
work ethic and time in the office, time
in front of the screens.
Um
you might even argue it's the the most
important above intellectual ability,
above
uh you know, natural talent. Some people
don't believe in natural talent.
Um
and that the work ethic is what gets you
gets you through the the hard times.
>> Mhm.
What do you think the single greatest
rule is in trading?
>> Single greatest rule?
Uh man.
Um
single greatest rule.
I think uh Alpha Trader uh author Brent
Donnelly said it best. Traders
uh
traders need to
have Let me get this right. I don't
misquote him.
Uh
traders have strong opinions loosely
held.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay.
Yeah, I wanted to ask that after your
examples because it sounded like uh
what's going on is yeah, just not
cutting the losers, not cut you know,
you have the traders that are
not cutting those losers and letting the
winners letting the winners
>> honest, that's probably the smallest of
uh the
pretty much everybody that gets to this
stage of the game has read every book,
knows all the core principles.
Everything that can be taught from a
book is known.
Um it's available to everybody. It's out
there on the internet. It's out there in
books.
Everybody knows that that's the that
that's the game.
Um and very rarely do I see that as a as
a problem with people that get indoor to
where we are where working
with them.
But the single greatest rule, maybe the
I think the single greatest rule is
there are no single greatest rules.
Everything
everything needs to be
taken together and worked on together
from from risks to edge to
work ethic. But yeah, again, if you if
you're not taking care of any one of
those, all the the other ones don't
don't work. If you don't have edge and
you're just but you have amazing
discipline, you're just managing a
slowly rotting
you know, pile of capital.
If you have
no discipline, but you've got edge,
again, there's the other side of
problems. They all you know, they all
work together.
>> So, having the edge, having the
discipline, having the consistency to
compound, they they all kind of work
together, but there's the one of them
which you say is constantly changing and
you have to keep innovating and that is
edge. I'm curious for you, what how do
you at what point do you realize, okay,
this edge is becoming decayed, perhaps,
and what signals that to you to the
point where you say, "Look, I'm back in
the
>> Losses, man. Losses signal that, dude.
>> [laughter]
>> Losses no longer
>> After what [clears throat] period of
time? How many losses?
>> That I don't think there's a specific
rule, but you know,
you go to the trade and the trade either
doesn't line up and it just it's not
there anymore or it just lines up a lot
less frequently and the edge just slowly
disappears with without losses. You're
just not making any money.
Um some trades are lining up and you
think it's good, but it just goes bad.
Um I've got a few of those at the moment
that I'm wrestling with.
Um and it's it's hard cuz you you get
pretty attached to making money in
certain parts of the day and uh
when one of those pieces of edge starts
going away, you've got to You eye on it.
You drop size.
You manage it like any other
losing part of life. You restrict
yourself to trading it how you trade it.
Tighter downside.
And then ultimately got to sort of make
the call or just more patient
or trade it in a different way, you
know.
You know, it might be a fading strategy
that fade that just works forever and
ever and ever and then all of a sudden
it stops working and then maybe the
trade is then to just go with it.
Um
but it's yeah, it'll be losses,
frequency of the trade. I had this one
trade
that I I used to trade the VIX and I
used to trade it in pretty big size.
Size that terrified the the risk
managers and I would a lot of times I'd
have them on the phone in case I lost
connectivity or something. The risk was
so big that I just wanted to have an an
out to be able to delete orders.
Um but this trade was would line up two,
three times a week.
Six, seven, eight times a month. And
and I could trade really big size.
And then the Ukraine war started.
And that trade
vanished. Never came back. And I was
trading this for I don't know, two,
three, four years where every other day
the trade was there and it's and the
first, second day of the most recent
Ukraine war um
uh or should say the invade Russian
invasion.
Um
that edge just disappeared and the trade
came back maybe one or two times over
the next maybe three or four months and
then it never came back again.
Sometimes it just disappears, you know,
either a market participant is trading
in a different way. A market participant
realizes they're trading in a bad way.
Um or just some scenario where it was
working changes and the trade is gone.
>> I'm sure your students would love you to
expand on that edge since it's no longer
around. Tell us a little bit about it.
Are you free, too? Or not this one here?
>> Uh it was a reoccurring It was a
reoccurring order.
Somebody would come in every
every 10 seconds at a or 20 seconds or
30 seconds at a specific time of day and
would buy
a random amount of size. They're trying
to It looked like they were trying to
hide the size. But the
frequency at which they were coming to
market was the same. So, they might
trade a 25 lot and then a 35 lot and
then a 50 lot and then a 10 lot and then
a five lot, but it was coming in every
10 seconds or every 15 seconds or or
every 10 to 15 seconds. They would try
to put in like a randomized
entry time, but you could still see it
because
it was just really
it was they would come in at a quiet
time of day and you could see the orders
coming through
and you could trade with them. They were
moving the market cuz they were coming
in every 10 seconds and they'd have a
pretty big size to do and that would
move the market and you could go with
them. And then at a specific time of day
they would just stop.
And then you get to liquidate
>> and you reverse.
>> I would liquidate and sometimes reverse,
yeah.
>> Liquidate sometimes reverse.
>> Oh, incredible. Now, when you saw us
like the for this edge specifically,
let's let me ask um
are you How do you scale these
positions? Are you are you kind of
putting multiple lots out there as well
or are you going single entry? How do
you manage that position?
>> Uh I would say I mostly go single entry
and there's some trades that I should
scale and I need to scale more with, but
that's a constant wrestling.
That's a That's a That's a constant
challenge, I think, for for for traders
is to
is to add to your winners.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh whereas adding to your loser seems to
be really easy.
>> You're right.
>> Um, it's it's almost like a natural
instinct to just want to
>> [snorts]
>> sell at 10 and then woo, 14, that's an
even better price to sell at. That's
even higher.
Um, whereas, you know, you sell 10s and
now it's at eights, now it's at sevens,
sixes. Adding to that winner is is
more psychologically difficult.
>> Yeah.
>> Um,
and I I I find the rule in trading is
that if it is difficult, it's the right
decision.
Whereas if it's easy, it's the wrong
>> I'm writing that down. That is that is
so good. You know, we had on Eduardo,
another guest here recently, and he
said, "If it's you know, you got to make
yourself uncomfortable because that's
when you grow." And you're saying
something along the same lines, like if
if it's uncomfortable, likely it's the
right decision. But, you know, it makes
sense because why would that why would
that be? If you think, traders, if you
want to be not among the 90% of traders,
you got to kind of do what the 90% are
not doing, and that's exactly what
you're you're saying. Like this is not
comfortable for me to do, therefore I
should do it.
>> Generally speaking, the the harder it is
and more difficult it is to do is
because you're fighting the human
in nor like natural human emotion or the
natural human choice.
And you know, the natural human choice
is to hold a loser and hope that it
turns into a winner. And the natural
human choice for winners is to take the
money off the table
as soon as it's uh showing green. And
that's the you know, that's the classic
classic human emotion uh scenario. But,
there's lots of these in trading where
it's just difficult to put on the trade,
either the market's moving too much or
the order book looks like it's stacked
against you.
Um, you know, pullbacks, looks like it's
changing uh changing direction where
it's actually just a pullback and you
know, how do you know? But, generally
speaking, like you said, the the harder
it is to do,
usually it's the the the right answer.
>> And that's where systematic traders
would come in and say, you know, you
start developing, you know, that that
systematic approach. And I know you said
you have some trades that are you're
taking that approach as well. How many
edges, I'm curious, how many edges do
you do you trade? Do you currently
trade?
>> I got about probably 20 to 40 different
types of edge and trades that I do on an
average day.
>> Incredible. And you kind of break those
down into different I like the poker
analogy, right? So, do you break those
down into oh, this is pocket ace, I'm
putting more risk on, this is pocket two
>> Oh, yeah, for sure, yeah.
>> seven two offsuit, so
>> Oh, yeah, absolutely.
You know, absolutely. Like there's some
where I will take as much size as the
market will will give me. There are some
where I'm trading a one lot in the S&P,
you know. It's uh it it's very much
depends on
uh the piece of edge that that shows up
and the advantage that is available from
from my own research
um and the dislocation that's actually
in the market.
>> So, I'm curious for you, Jason, what
like the the market's ever-changing. Um
I'm curious with how you see the future
of trading going, if there's room for,
you know, point and click traders in the
future with the way AI's going or for
example, you know, we have the PDT rule
here in the US changing, so there's
going to be more um traders more
availability for traders to trade. So,
what do you think edges are going to be
more systematic over time? Is there room
for discretionary traders and what what
traders do you think are going to
survive over the next decade? How do you
see the landscape?
>> Sure. Um markets are always going to go
up and down, so it's there's always
going to be opportunity for for people
to uh to trade. Um edges will change,
you know, just like when trading
electronic trading first, you know, the
transition from the floor to the to
electronic trading, some people made the
transition. Some people didn't. And then
you had the change when it was everybody
was point and click uh in the first days
of of electronic trading and then slowly
um people started building algorithms
and automated trading and that changed
the way the market moved and trades that
were available on point click
for point click people, you know, a
bunch of those disappeared and evolved
into some other some other trade, but a
lot of people weren't able to make that
transition.
Um and then you've got
AI for sure involved, machine learning
for sure involved, but you know, at
every stage of of
sort of that trading evolution
some people have maintained [snorts]
their abilities in the market and
adapted and maintained and other people
haven't. I think that whole
you know, training keeping me staying in
the training mindset helps people adapt
to to the new scenarios when when old
ways of trading stop working um and new
technologies come in and change the the
landscape, but I think the markets are
always going to go up and down
and algos aren't some perfect, you know,
terminator
robot
you know, market killer. They make
mistakes as well. You know, the algos
and the automated trading systems are
only as good as the people that program
them and come up with the ideas and
concepts on how to execute those algos
and high frequency trades. So, you know,
algos still make mistakes and and we we
prey on algos and hope for algos to make
mistakes in the markets as well. And
then when the markets get busy like the
last month and a half or so, you know, a
lot of times algos
pull out and high frequency traders and
the automated traders will pull out and
the markets get a lot looser and more
opportunities show up because the
volatility is so much higher and their
their algos and high frequency trades
aren't built to deal with the level of
volatility that the markets have seen.
So,
I have no doubt that trading for
whatever style you have is is always
going to be available and there to to
participants. Markets aren't going away.
If anything, they're becoming deeper,
bigger, and more available to to people.
And for creative,
hard-working, innovative people, you're
just going to find more and more
opportunities.
I think one thing that stands out for me
from when I started in the beginning in
the late '90s or 2000s, it was it was
pretty easy to be consistent and make a
small amount of money, but it was really
hard to make big money. Whereas I find
now, it's much harder to get consistent
and to get that baseline of performance.
But once you're there, it's a lot easier
to make a lot more money in these
markets today than it was when I first
started.
>> [snorts]
>> Ever watch a stock rip and think, "I
could have nailed that if I had real
capital?" The truth is, many capable
traders never reach their potential. Not
due to lack of skill, but lack of scale.
Trade The Pool was built to solve
exactly that. A firm designed for
serious individuals who want access to
the US equity markets with meaningful
buying power, up to $200,000 without
committing their own capital. Get access
to virtually every stock and ETF. Go
long or short freely with the
flexibility professional traders expect.
You're evaluated on one thing, your
ability to manage risk and execute with
consistency. Meet the standard and you
trade at scale. No subscriptions, no
ongoing commitments. Whether you're
still refining your strategy, a trader
with experience who hasn't yet broken
through, or a seasoned professional
simply looking for more capital, Trade
The Pool is built to meet you where you
are and take you that next step further.
The markets have evolved, access has
evolved, now so has the way traders
operate within them. Trade The Pool.
pool.
>> 1999 versus now. What do you attribute
that to? Is it the increased volatility
because you've lived through some very
volatile
uh times, you know, with the 9/11 and
then '08. Uh you've traded through those
and then COVID. Uh do you think it's the
increased volatility?
>> I think it is a mix of increased
volatility um in the market, you know, I
I'll give you one example is that I used
to trade uh
the uh
Euro Stoxx in uh in Europe and it would
have a daily range of
you know, 15 or 20 ticks, 15 or 20
prices.
And uh now it has a range in excess of
100 150 prices
um on a regular basis. So, volatility is
definitely much higher.
Um and I think volume is much higher.
Um and that you're able to get off a lot
more size than than it used to. In that
Euro Stoxx example, I remember 100 lot
being uh massive size in that and you
could lean against it and sell in front
of it until it got down to and you watch
a trade goes down to 90 then down to 80
and then to 70 and then down to 60. When
it gets to 60, you you cover your
position and uh when it gets to 50 and
then 40, you reverse the position. And
then it goes.
Um whereas now a 100 lot is invisible in
that market um and you can trade
hundreds anytime you want.
Uh
so, I think the mix of volatility being
greater, size being greater in most
markets.
Um and then there's also diversity of
markets. When I first started, we
probably traded four different markets
and now
you know, I'm looking at six, seven,
eight different exchanges in front of me
and hundreds and hundreds of markets.
Uh so, it's
it's size and scale is much greater on
on almost every on every measure every
every measurement.
>> And you're very prepared, you know, from
doing the research you're
the next event's not going to surprise
you, is it Jason? I mean, you've you've
talked about your you're very prepared
for whatever the world brings and your
react like your reaction, you don't have
to necessarily think about it because
you've already thought about it.
>> That's the ideal,
um but
again there's probably an area I could
probably be more disciplined with is my
preparation for specific events. Um you
know, you generally look to see how
how stuff is traded in the past to give
you an indication of what it's going to
trade like in the future
um and you get event scenarios
in your mind written down to tell you
how a market is going to trade or not
trade and then your preparation tells
you that when that news kicks off
instead of thinking about, you know,
spending the 10 seconds or 20 seconds or
2 minutes to think about how is this how
is my market going to react to this
news? You've already thought about it
and you're just executing.
>> It's brilliant. So you've traded now for
nearly three decades. Um
>> I wish you'd stop saying that, man.
>> [laughter]
>> Well
Hey, it's it's the wisdom and the
experience. And I just want to I'm
curious what the what the next what the
next three decades what what do they
hold for Jason?
Um
over the course of the next 30 years and
then
you know, what
what keeps you so passionate as well? I
mean
is your passion
now for just as strong as ever or are
you more passionate now about training,
you know, the next generation of
traders?
Uh
what's the next 30 years hold for you?
>> Uh
I think I'm a dopamine junkie and I just
love clicking the mouse.
Uh trading is is like video games. It's
like
it's like getting that hit from, you
know, watching your Facebook or
Instagram page or text messages coming
in. There's a certain amount of like I
won't say addiction to trading, but
there is a pleasure that is definitely
dopamine related to trading.
And it's the same like I really enjoy
video games.
My my wife does not enjoy that I enjoy
video games, but I I really enjoy video
games, but I understand that they are
pleasurable to me because of the
effect of that the body generates
dopamine and the brain likes it. And I
think trading has a certain degree of
that as well. But I've always just been
involved in competitive sports or
competitive activities, whether it's
basketball, baseball, tennis, whatever.
Trading and video games and competitive
card games was never super into poker. I
mean, I played at the casinos with my
family and stuff. We'd always go to
blackjack table, but I didn't I never
liked playing the way they liked because
I always knew that [clears throat] even
if we were playing blackjack, the best
odds in the casino, this before Texas
Hold'em was there,
that the odds were still not in my
favor. And so they would go crazy in the
casinos and they would all, you know,
spend their allotted 200 bucks or
whatever.
But I never got I would play with them,
but never with the same passion because
I always knew the numbers were against
me.
Whereas in trading and in sports in
video games, you know, the the
the playing field is level in many
regards. Obviously in sports, you know,
you can't be playing with pros if you're
not a pro.
But I just love the competition. I love
the competition with the other guys in
the office in you know, trading with the
with trainees and
and hearing how they have developed and
seeing that I put on the trade
and they put on the trade and even
though they might be at different
amounts of size to see you know what did
I hold did I hold to the to the right
exit spot did they hold to the right
exit spot and it's not that I'm happy
that I beat them but I'm happy that I
competed with them and enjoy that
process of of friendly competition. Um
and sports, games, trading
all of those all of those have that
element of competition and I and I'm 50
years old and playing basketball twice a
week and none of my family my my wife is
like how how why why do you play and I
just I just love the competition and I
love the the the teamwork required to
play basketball. I love the teamwork
that's required to to trade
um and that just sense of competition
and teamwork and then achievement like
you know the last month and a half has
been really good in the markets and all
of your work both for me as an
individual and all of my work with the
with the guys around me really you can
really see it come to fruition when
markets like this kick off and trainees
go from being trainees to becoming you
know full-blown traders cuz they've
gotten hold of the markets and done
things that even I didn't do. Um so it's
really great to see that progress but
that again you know I said it earlier
about
trading in a team environment trading in
an environment where there's other
people around you. Yeah I I I think I
just got I really enjoy
uh being part of a team and what the
team accomplishes and
you know
you compare yourself a little bit to the
guys around you but it's friendly
comparison
and you know that if you are you know
there's some guys that just always
outperform you and there's some guys
that always under perform you and if the
guy who under perform you under performs
you normally outperform you you kind of
you know you ask yourself questions like
what did I do right what did I do wrong
or
maybe it's less about me and it's just
more he had a great day. Um I just
really enjoy the, you know, friendly
competition environment. And uh trading
is where you, you know, you put your
brain and uh your balls on the into the
market and you get out a specific
result.
And
whether that's
just pride of ability or it is the
dopamine talking.
Um, I I really enjoy that
that this type of environment.
>> You know, I've heard of this, you know,
the dopamine rush is certainly there.
And I caution, I've always cautioned
traders, you know, with that with where
certainly you can be cognizant of it and
it not be used as a weapon against you,
but there's this thing called a scarcity
loop, which it certainly falls under and
you actually pointed that out as well
with
you know, social media how you you have
these three components of it that is
quick repeatability,
random results,
um, and opportunity that's present. And
if you think about those three, it's not
it's it's casinos, slot machines,
Facebook, TikTok, all the dating apps,
and even video games. Like yeah,
everything can fall in in that category.
And so we just have to
really be on our guard that, you know,
we're we're applying that discipline.
Yes, there's a dopamine rush, but yes,
we also have to apply that discipline,
you know, as well. So, I'm I'm curious
for you though is have you had any of
your trainees outperform even you?
>> Absolutely, yeah. My partners always are
always telling me that Jason, we're
being a successful firm is when uh
trainees and traders are outperforming
you. Oh, yeah. No, on a on a regular
basis. You know, I I
I might be the the face of uh this firm
and uh I'm here talking to you uh
because I'm in the book, but uh I think
there would uh easily be uh an you know,
another
two or three or four guys that could
easily be in the in the book and the the
trade
as well if not better. Definitely trade
better
than me.
>> And I've had the pleasure of reading
your part in it. It's excellent. It's
coming out June 2026. For those that are
watching either prior to that date or
after, make sure you pre-order or order.
That book is it's it's an amazing
amazing incredible read. It's going to
add tremendous value to your trading. So
lastly, Jason, I want to ask you just uh
your advice for traders trying to build
longevity.
Uh final words over to you.
>> Boy, that's a that's a big question. Um
I I I probably say that the shortest and
most difficult answer there is
get yourself inside a firm.
Um and uh
that is the I think that is the single
greatest source of edge and longevity
that you can do as an individual.
Um and do it in an environment where you
have lots of time to develop as a
trader. And if you get to a certain part
in your career after, you know, being
with that firm for a number of years
that you say, "Okay, the firm isn't
giving me the value that I want." then
maybe I'll go somewhere else. Um but I
really think that surrounding yourself
with other successful talented
hard-working people rubs off on you, you
rub off on them, and that uh
that continuing circle
leads to people having greater levels of
success than if you were trading by
yourself. Now, the difficulty is that
there's not everybody has access to a to
a firm in their in their town
or their city or wherever they live. Um
but uh doing your best to
solve for that problem and moving to a
place where you can get jobs at firms is
I think the the
solution that I would encourage people
to uh to attempt. If you can't do that,
then you're on a you're just you're at
so much of a disadvantage
compared to other participants in the
market. You know, when you go to a firm
or you speaking of even from just my own
firm's stats, if we hire you,
it's a 40
60 40 50 60% chance that you're going to
become a successful trader to some
degree, whether it's
you know, low, medium or high levels of
success, you will get to that level of
success,
you know, four, five, six people out of
10.
Whereas if you are trying this on your
own,
you're looking at one out of 100,
one out of 200, one out of and you know,
at worst one out of 1,000, you know.
There are lots of people that attempt
this because trading is so prevalent and
so easily accessible these days that I
think everybody gets the impression that
it's easy to do because you can have all
the tools in front of you
and it it gives this to yourself sort of
a false hope that just because I have
all these tools in front of me, I
am in the position of being successful
in the long term, whereas that isn't the
case for most people. That's not not
saying that, you know, there are there
are those one in 100 or one in 1,000
people that do become successful and I
think there are
I think there are even a couple in the
in the Market Wizards book, but that the
odds are very, very slim and that you
want to do everything you can to make
those odds more in your favor and I
think the best way to do that is to
find yourself a firm
or
maybe even just find yourself a small
group of people that you can work with
that you can learn from each other,
develop and just be surrounded by other
smart successful people.
>> Incredible. And traders, we should
certainly listen to Jason because he is
Mr.
Consistency. So, he knows what he's
talking about. The results are
incredible over all these years,
specifically because I mean, the markets
have changed so much, you know, from
uh the outcry to the
electronic trading to algorithm. But,
you know, the one thing traders has
stayed consistent in all of that is
Jason's level of performance.
So, his
trading, especially around risk control
innovation, which was pointed out many
times, and that trainee mindset that
we've discussed here in today's episode,
really challenges the idea that
experience alone might actually be
enough.
Uh it's clear, Jason, that in your world
edge
isn't something you find once, it's
something that you just keep
rediscovering over and over and over
again. And I I think your perspective on
building traders is just as valuable as
your own trading.
Uh
training so many, you know, hundreds of
traders,
and uh seeing how different people
respond to the pressure, loss,
opportunity,
and what separates those who make it
from those who don't. So,
Jason, we really appreciate you taking
the time today to share your your
journey, the insights, uh all the great
valuable lessons that you've taught us
here today. So, for the for those
listening out there that
>> [snorts]
>> want to follow your work,
uh where can they find you?
>> Uh Twitter and uh LinkedIn. Uh I think
uh JasonHBarry on uh on Twitter and uh
JasonBarry on uh on LinkedIn.
>> [clears throat]
>> Perfect.
Well, Jason, thank you so much for
coming on Chat with Traders.
>> Hey, thanks for having me. Keep doing a
great job, We I I know all of myself and
all of my traders we uh we love
listening to the episodes and and learn
just as much from uh from you as we do
from ourselves. Thank you.
>> We appreciate you. Take care.
>> Take care.
>> You've reached the end of this episode
of Chat with Traders. But, rest assured,
there are more episodes loaded with real
market insight and zero hype on the way
soon. So, to stay updated with [music]
each great new release, subscribe to the
podcast, and we'd love it if you'd leave
a rating and review. We'll catch you
next [music] time on Chat With Traders.
>> [music]
[music]